this is a good training kya 527 in
Samadhi Sutton it's a short suitor but
you know some interesting point points
that can be impact so it starts by
saying bhikkhus developed limitless
intelligent recollected composure
because by developing limitless
limitless intelligent recollect the
composure 5 knowledge ease arise for
oneself which 5 the knowledge the first
knowledge e this composure is currently
Pleasant and in the future the result
will be pleasant the word for Pleasant
suka so it can also be translated as e
easy ease this this composure is
currently resulting in ease and any
future result will be also the same so
and that is it's not a pleasure
whichever way you were to choose to
translate it it's not it's not obviously
the central kind as the Buddha would
often describe that but it also it's not
a physical kind either it's it's that's
why I wanted to say the alternative of
ease because you don't necessarily feel
ease spesific Lee as a sensation in your
body or something that you can kind of
observe in that manner it's more of in
of a state that's experienced on the
extension level so freedom from threat
for example is something that would
result in you experiencing an ease of
that of the general kind freedom from
danger seclusion from from things that bother
seclusion from from things that bother
you that could cause you concern
so all of that if you were to surmount
it has to result in ease and so if you
were to practice their boundless or
limitless type of composure it would have to
type of composure it would have to
result in these that's the first first
type of knowledge you would recognize
that mmm so the second type of knowledge
is oh it says it this composure is Noble
not of the flesh so it's not it's not
pertaining to a sensual ecstatic
pleasure or anything like that it's
basically on the level of the mind it's
on the level of the mind and it results
in that existential leads from from from
threat from being prayed to suffering
from any anything that sort of burdened
you the back of your mind emotionally
and so on then the third knowledge is
that this composure is not not
associated with inferior men so that
means that in order to have this
composure you need to have wisdom it needs to be
you need to have wisdom it needs to be
it needs to be understood and developed
in the level on that level it's not it's
not it cannot happen to accidentally
cannot stumble upon it you cannot not be
restrained not make the effort towards
that self strengthening of that
composure and obtain this type of
meditation that's impossible
so anything they will make inferior
which is great a virgin delusion is not
something that you can that can result
in this type of knowledge in this type
of composure so you have to abandon the
inferiority in that sense internally in
order to partake to this knowledge
default knowledge is the the knowledge
that this composure is peaceful elevated
obtained through calming reach by
unification not by suppressing holding
back or obstructing cigars the
determinations so this is probably the
most condensed line of the Sutra and
before we
before we get into it again just the
suit is called samadhi Sutra and Samadhi
is composure it's not concentration you
can have composure without a colloquial
sense of concentration but obviously you
can't have concentration with a
composure but Samadhi is much more than
just concentration and more more more
often than not practically speaking when
people take or when people think of
concentration you think about focusing
by definition that's what concentrating
is focusing on a particular object at
the expense of everything else Samadhi
is opposite of that we said that many
times before but it doesn't repeat it
it's it's composing it's bringing things
together not excluding everything on
account of one point but basically
developing the type of composure that
doesn't exclude any fundamental aspects
of your experience such as perception
feeling intentions and so on that's
that's addressed in in many other
suitors so it's important to keep
reiterating that because many people
would waste tremendous amount of effort
in in just concentrating and
concentrating and expecting a certain
like a release at experience to come out
of it but Samadhi is opposite of
focusing on one point which basically
one point limits you one point is
limiting and one point is your boundary
you focusing on sensations the tip of
your nostrils belly whatever meditation
object you might have taken means you're
doing it at expense of everything else
as I mentioned before and that cannot be
called limitless in boundless there is
nothing boundless about it you're bound
literally by one point so that I mean
it's the opposite direction of common
assumption of concentration practice
that's why Samadhi mindfulness
hand-in-hand one results in the other
with fortifies it
so composure that is intelligent based
on wisdom based on mindfulness based on
based on recollected nests as the as the
as the opening opening lines of this so
to say so it's important to keep that in
mind it's it's there general recollect
Ness that then you crack the den you
sort of fortified into a sense of
compulsion literally like compose
yourself it's somebody just tells you so
putting aside anything you know you
think you might know anything you heard
about meditation is somebody were to
tell you compose yourself how would you
do it would you do it by focusing on
your nose through the soles of your feet
no you wouldn't you just bring yourself
back into your experience as a whole as
in recognize that you couldn't have left
it even if you wanted to and then you
full and close by so you stop ignoring
it so compose yourself mean stop
ignoring your current experience as a
whole that's it that's why if we fully
developed Samadhi we'll have to approve
the attitude of ignoring which is what
the VJ is ignoring things of the
unpleasant kind usually so composure
then means bringing yourself together
and recollecting yourself keeping
yourself composed the more you practice
that the more it is going to develop so
the fault knowledge is recognition that
this type of composure is peaceful
elevated got through calming reach by
unification so that's that's the point
here calming calm yourself down do you know
calming calm yourself down do you know
how to do that do you do you recognize
what to attend how to attend they will
have to result in calmness or do you
just go through a set of motions that
sort of approximate the idea of what
calmness is and then you hope calmness
will happen to it well if it's the
letter it means you're not doing it
right Li you want to develop summary
where you know what calmness is you know
how to do it and you know how to attend
to it they will have to come you from
anything that has been disturbing you
so this composure is peaceful elevated
got through calming reach by unification
and that's again how do you unify things
you unify things by focusing on one
point that
cludes everything else that's not
unification that separation or do you
unified by not taking up a point an
object of your meditation and discerning
just universal nature of whatever you're
experiencing at a time that becomes your
container and by definition that's
already a form of unification
so you unify all these diverse aspects
the all these feelings that I feel
throughout the day well you unify them
by being composed upon the nature of
felt whatever is felt doesn't matter
pleasant unpleasant neutral doesn't
matter on account of sight sound smell taste
on account of sight sound smell taste
touch thoughts doesn't matter how
diverse feelings might be you know
feeling is there there you go that's all
in the form of unification
so this composure is peaceful elevated
go through calming reach by unification
not by suppressing holding back pretty
much concentrating oops and obstructing
the determinations and that's what the
terminations is knowing what things are
there they determine your calmness or
determine your lack of it knowing what
is there in your experience as a whole
that undermines your composure or
establishes it so knowledge of
determinations means knowledge of
Samadhi knowing how to attend
determinations in sin Cara's means
basically knowing how to practice
Samadhi and and then the fifth knowledge
is i entered upon this meditation this
type of composure
this composure I'm gonna say type
because this is the composure to the
Buddha approves off which means that the
composure that should be developed no
other no other type of it so the fifth
knowledge is that I enter upon this
composure with recollect Ness I emerge
from it with recollectionist so it does
not just happen to you so you don't have
a clue how this boundless composure has
a reason no you know exactly I came to
be and you exactly when it's ceasing to
be and that's what means I interpret
with recollectionist you have fully
recollected so there is no lapsing in
your in your mindfulness you
new establishment upon experience as a
whole subsequent of your mind when you
enter this boundlessness it's in in
other words it's not a mystical
experience it's not experience of some
you know undescribable indescribable
sense of cessation and boundlessness and
limitless in the you can't put in the
words no you can very well put it in the
words and the Buddha just did he said
these are the five knowledge that you
can use to describe this very type of
composure but the fundamental
characteristic is there is absolutely no
compromising of your mindfulness of your
recollect earnest of your sati it's the
basis for this composure and even when
you leave this composer that sati
remains so if there is sati if there is
composure upon sati there is no focusing
practice of concentration upon one thing
or the other and then having this lofty
extraordinarily pleasant experience come
over you like basically possess you for
a while and then and it is just ecstatic
or extremely Pleasant whichever way you
want to describe it no pleasure means
ease composure means opposite of
concentration based upon the recollected
Ness it requires wisdom because it's it
it requires wisdom because it's it
cannot be obtained by inferior man it's
noble not of the flesh does not pertain
to anything that you can feel pleasantly
by any of the senses and you can only be
entered upon through mindfulness through
through recollect earnest and emerge
from it on the basis of recollect
earnest